Wickham family papers MSS 15753
Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library
- Correspondence of the Wickham and related families
  - Family correspondence – Williams Carter Wickham (1820-1888) with his wife, Lucy Penn Taylor Wickham (1830-1913) and young children, 1861 August-October; 1 folder(s) (Box 11, Folder 10)
    Wickham is in Cavalry Camp, 5th Brigade and attached to Colonel Cocke's Brigade and has a complete blacksmith shop and blacksmith fixed up with his company but requires clothes for his [slave?] Robin (September 1, 1861); Many letters discuss conditions of camp life for an officer in the Confederate forces and the efforts of family at home to supply the needs and wants of their own family members in the forces but also those of other soldiers, such as clothing. The letters also show a desire to establish a local hospital for the troops like the ones run by the ladies in Fredericksburg, Virginia (September 4, 1861); Wickham writes from his camp at Fairfax Courthouse about opportunities for drilling the troops, his resignation of his seat in the Convention and in the Virginia Senate, his increasing concerns over the conduct of the war in the last two months, and the injurious effect of the capture of Fort Hatteras in North Carolina to the South (September 6, 1861); news that his son, Henry T. Taylor, is intensely reading the novels of Sir Walter Scott to the detriment of his studies (September 26, 1861); clothing made by the ladies of the community shipped off to the troops (October 12, 1861); Wickham currently at Union Mills (October 22, 1861); the difficulties of Lizzie Fry in getting a permit to leave to go home (October 24, 1861); and Wickham's meeting with General [Jeb] Stuart with whom he is very pleased (October 27, 1861).
  - Family correspondence – Williams Carter Wickham (1820-1888) with his wife, Lucy Penn Taylor Wickham (1830-1913) and young children, 1861 November-December; 1 folder(s) (Box 11, Folder 11)
    Wickham writes a very detailed letter about the detrimental effects of fighting the Civil War on their own home soil, his dinner with General Cocke, whose ardor for the war has cooled considerably, the wasting of their best resources in an unnatural strife, and the devastation wrought by both occupying armies (November 3, 1861); and mention of Colonel Robertson and General Stuart (November 7, 13, and 29, 1861). Writing from Camp Frontier after an absence of three days, he describes a plan for a force of nine companies of cavalry and three regiments of infantry, all under General Stuart, to cut off an enemy encampment near Alexandria, but this was prevented by the arrival of more Federal forces in the area near Pohick Church and describes his activities as a member of the scouting party (November 13, 1861); furnishes a description of his strategy when in new territory (November 21, 1861); shares his belief that the Yankees will advance along the Evansport line, chiefly by water, but with a land force on the telegraph road, otherwise believes that they will go into winter quarters (November 24, 1861); and repeats a report from Mr. Porcher [of South Carolina?] that some of the coloured people had been shot by the Confederates and that some of the people offered to work on the entrenchments for the Yankees for pay (November 28, 1861). Wickham is still waiting for word on any advancement against the enemy and a describes the Federal forces arrayed against Virginia (December 4, 1861); Wickham shares his wish to command a full regiment of cavalry if he cannot have his first preference to be at home with Lucy, his shock at hearing about the death of Mr. [Cooke?] and his efforts to secure a furlough for Church to go home for the funeral (December 14, 1861).
  - Family correspondence – Williams Carter Wickham (1820-1888) with his wife, Lucy Penn Taylor Wickham (1830-1913) and young children, 1862 January-February; 1 folder(s) (Box 12, Folder 1)
    Wickham writes about the following topics, a story about Lt. Colonel Thomas L. Kane, commander of the Bucktail Rifles of Northern Pennsylvania and a relative (January 2, 1862); General Johnston likes Wickham's bill for the better organization of the army (January 8, 1862); Wickham's [slave?], Robin, has built a wonderful shelter for the horses in their winter camp (January 8, 1862); Wickham returns to Camp Ewell after his furlough (January 29, 1862); his disapproval of the bill in the Senate concerning the Virginia forces (February 4, 1862); and he expresses concerns over the reorganization of his regiment (February 15, 1862).
  - Family correspondence – Williams Carter Wickham (1820-1888) with his wife, Lucy Penn Taylor Wickham (1830-1913) and young children, 1862 March-April; 1 folder(s) (Box 12, Folder 2)
    Topics include the alarm of the people in the area north of the Rappahannock where people are abandoning their homes and Negroes are going northward by the hundreds (March 14, 1862); bivouacking comfortably near Brandy Station (April 4, 1862); and reports that their new location is twelve miles below Williamsburg and five miles from Yorktown at "Blows Mill" and that they are short on provisions (April 18, 22 and 24, 1862).
  - Family correspondence – Williams Carter Wickham (1820-1888) with his wife, Lucy Penn Taylor Wickham (1830-1913) and young children, 1862 August-December; 1 folder(s) (Box 12, Folder 3)
    Topics include writing from Sudley Mills describes recent events that have greatly reduced his regiment and prevented his communicating with his family, noting that with 200 men Wickham charged the 12th Pennsylvania Cavalry 800 strong, routing them and capturing a large number, mentioning that General Ewell has lost a leg [during the battle of Groveton] (August 30, 1862); currently near Frederick, Maryland (September 7, 1862); yesterday at Sharpsburg, Maryland, "fought probably the most desperate battle of the war" [Battle of Antietam], Wickham lost twenty men killed, wounded or missing, W.H.F. Lee's horse fell with him, Lt. Colonel Thornton of the 3rd had his arm torn by a shell and died of shock, Hill Carter received two severe wounds at Boonsborough and was left in the hands of the enemy, very difficult to find anything to eat, as local people will not sell them anything, and Thomas L. Kane was just made a Brigadier General in the Union army (September 18 and 21, 1862). Reports on his safe return from an expedition to Pennsylvania with 1800 men (October 14 and 19, 1862); details of the cavalry raid to collect horses from Mercersburg, Chambersburg, and Emmitsburg (October 19, 1862); troops destroying the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad (October 21, 1862); his participation recently in a serious battle with losses of 1500 killed or wounded [Battle of Fredericksburg], with the town of Fredericksburg totally devastated and mentions activities of Major General Ambrose Burnside (December 15 and 18, 1862).
  - Family correspondence – Williams Carter Wickham (1820-1888) with his wife, Lucy Penn Taylor Wickham (1830-1913) and young children, 1863 January-May; 1 folder(s) (Box 12, Folder 4)
    Topics include the rejection of his resignation by the Secretary of War (January 15, 1863); staying with General Robert E. Lee at Culpeper Courthouse (March 1, 1863); discussion of the [Battle of Chancellorsville] (May 8, 1863 copy); spent the day with Lee who was in good spirits but without any hope of quick termination of the war and who would not allow his resignation, and General Jackson said to be dangerously ill with pleurisy (May 10, 1863); mentions the death of General Jackson and his fears for the safety of General Lee who he describes in appreciative terms (May 11, 1863); and describes his visit to General Lee's headquarters and assesses the results of recent battles (May 31, 1863).
  - Family correspondence – Williams Carter Wickham (1820-1888) with his wife, Lucy Penn Taylor Wickham (1830-1913) and young children, 1863 June-1864 February; 1 folder(s) (Box 12, Folder 5)
    Topics include Wickham's approval of the generals James Longstreet, A.P. Hill, and Richard S. Ewell (June 3, 1863); Lucy relates their losses during visits of the Yankees to "Hickory Hill" and "North Wales" plantations and the capture of Fitzhugh Lee out of his sick bed (July 25, 1863); Wickham writes from the headquarters of Wickham's Brigade, following his commission as Brigadier General (September 12, 1863); news of Julius Theodore Porcher being mortally wounded from members of the 10th South Carolina Regiment (December 1863); Lucy Wickham's visit with General Wickham near Charlottesville, Virginia (January 17, 21, 31, 1864); General Lee has issued the first order that has not received Wickham's admiration (February 8, 1864); and draft of a letter from Wickham to Captain J.E. Cook, describing his actions beginning on October 28, 1862 until November 3, 1862 (February 26, 1864).
  - Family correspondence – Williams Carter Wickham (1820-1888) with his wife, Lucy Penn Taylor Wickham (1830-1913) and young children, 1864 March-September; 1 folder(s) (Box 12, Folder 6)
    Topics include accompanying General Robert E. Lee to the anniversary of the Young Men's Christian Association of Poney's Brigade to hear a talk on the character of General [Stonewall?] Jackson (March 29, 1864); description of the pillaging of "Hickory Hill" by the Yankees and their threatening Uncle Hill Carter (June 5, 1864, June 1864, August 1, 1864); mention of General Sheridan (July 25, 1864); description of the devastation in the area around Culpeper and mention of [Jubal] Early (August 12, 1864); and Wickham, while stationed in Winchester, Virginia, describing the broad valley just prior to the Battle of Winchester (September 5, 8, and 10, 1864).
  - Family correspondence – Williams Carter Wickham (1820-1888) chiefly with his wife, Lucy Penn Taylor Wickham (1830-1913), 1867-1888; 1 folder(s) (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Family correspondence of Captain Williams Carter Wickham (1887-1985), son of Henry Taylor Wickham and Elise W. Barksdale Wickham, 1905-1924; 1 folder(s) (Box 12, Folder 8)
    Wickham attended the U.S. Naval Academy from 1904 until 1909 and most of the letters from this period were to his parents. There are also a few dating from his service aboard the U.S.S. Minnesota (1911) and the U.S.S. Smith (1913) addressed to them. Letters dated 1924 from Captain Wickham to his wife, Credilla Miller Wickham, were written while serving in the U.S. Asiastic Fleet aboard the U.S.S. Pillsbury when the navy summered at Chefoo [present day Yantai], China.
  - Family correspondence of Captain Williams Carter Wickham (1887-1985), son of Henry Taylor Wickham and Elise W. Barksdale Wickham, 1941, 1944; 1 folder(s) (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Family correspondence of Williams Carter Wickham (1917-1982), chiefly as a child, 1925-1944; 1 folder(s) (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondents: A-B, 1851-1919; 1 folder(s) (Box 13, Folder 1)
    Correspondents include: J.S.B. Alleyne (resolutions concerning the death of Dr. William F. Wickham in 1851); John B. Baldwin; L.M. Baldwin; Nannie P. Ballard; A.P. Bankhead; B. Johnson Barbour, John L. Barbour; Greta du Pont Barksdale (1891-1965); Phoebe [Barksdale?]; Marianna Elizabeth Barksdale (1796-1856) and her husband, William Jones Barksdale (1794-1859); Ann B. Berkeley; Letitia Glenn Biddle (1864-1950); John Minor Botts (1802-1869); Mary G. Braxton; Mary Carter Brickner; G. Thompson Brown; Alfred H. Byrd; E.H. Byrd and L.C. Byrd. Topics include a very detailed letter from John Minor Botts to General Williams Carter Wickham about the Civil War, particularly the requested transfer of Colonel Charles H. Wager from the infantry service to the cavalry, rumors about General Lee evacuating Virginia, complaints about the press stimulating the prejudices of the people, and rumors of a proposal to arm the slaves to help fight against the Northern forces (January 8, 1865).
  - Miscellaneous correspondents: C-F, 1840-[post 1941]; 1 folder(s) (Box 13, Folder 2)
    Correspondents include: Ellen J. Cackie; J.R. Campbell (damaged postal card only); B.B. Claike; George Colton; A. Coolidge; O.A. Crenshaw; M.W.T. Cumberland; John B. Custis; Laura G. Custis; J.S. Davis; Enid Deem; Martha Lee Doughty "To the Women of the Confederacy" (undated); Fanny Duncan; Georgina L. Featherstonhaugh; and Mary J. Foster. Topics include: a discussion of several books read by Laura G. Custis of Boston (May 25, no year) and a description of the past few months the Custis family were forced to stay in Versailles, France, due to illness and the onset of the Franco-Prussian War (March 30, [1871]).
  - Miscellaneous correspondents of the Carter family, 1857-1878; 1 folder(s) (Box 13, Folder 3)
    Correspondents include: Ellen Carter, Lizzie Carter, L.W. Carter, Mary Carter, and W[illiams?] Carter, Jr. Topics include: the concern of W[illiams] Carter, Jr. that his father make a will immediately so that the Confederacy will not get any of [his brother?] Charles' portion of the estate. He writes emphatically "I don't wish the South to get a cent – no country in the history of the world has so worked out its own destruction as the Southern portion of the U.S. America, and all Christendom will in history say, Amen – next to Sodom and Gomorrah" (February 3, 1862); W[illiams?] Carter, Jr. also asks that the slaves on both the North Wales and South Wales plantations be sent to Charlotte or some safe place so they will not be sold like cattle, mentioning all of the Tom and Sarah Fox family, Ben Napper and family, the Tom Brown and Harry Brown families, and other slaves by first name only (March 1, 1862).
  - Miscellaneous correspondents of the Carter family, 1840-1875; 1 folder(s) (Box 13, Folder 4)
    Correspondents include: A.W. Carter; Agnes M. Carter; Annie Carter; Betty Carter; E.H. Carter; Emily Carter; Fanny N. Carter; L.H. Carter, Louise Carter, Pauline Carter, Susan Roy Carter, Thomas B. Carter, Thomas H. Carter (1831-1908), and Williams Carter. Topics include: the death of Julia Wickham (Thomas H. Carter, July 19, 1873); an expression of hope that the nation will mend following the Civil War, saying "my hatred for Davis is only equaled by that for Charles Sumner," and mention of balloon flights and France's position of strength in Europe (Thomas B. Carter, Paris, May 22, 1866).
  - Miscellaneous correspondents: Mary Braxton [Randolph] Carter (1800-1864), chiefly to Anne Butler Carter Wickham and other family members, 1839-1862; 1 folder(s) (Box 13, Folder 5)
    Topics of note include two references to the Civil War, including the "suffering northern soldiers" and the sentiment "the same God made us all" (August 10, 1861); and a second letter about the Civil War concerning shelling of the area near Shirley along the river by northern gunboats and comments about [General John] Pope (August 28, 1862).
  - Miscellaneous correspondents: R[obert] R[andolph] Carter (1825-1888), [1862], 1872-1879; 1 folder(s) (Box 13, Folder 6)
    Topics include a condolence letter (July 12, 1873) concerning the death of Julia Leiper Wickham (1859-1873).
  - Miscellaneous Correspondents: of the Chevallie family and Warwick family, 1802, 1815-1860; 1 folder(s) (Box 13, Folder 7)
    Correspondents include: Peter J. Chevallie to his wife, Elizabeth Gilliam Chevallie; Sarah Magee "Sally" Chevallie Warwick (1816-1846) to her mother, Elizabeth Green Gilliam Chevallie (1796-1865); Joseph Gallego to his nephew, Peter J. Chevallie; Henry Chevallie to his sister, Mary G. Chevallie; and Abraham Warwick (1794-1874) to his daughter-in-law, Elise F. Warwick.
  - Miscellaneous correspondents: M.M. Fanning, 1875-1876; 1 folder(s) (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous correspondents: G-K, 1851-1943; 1 folder(s) (Box 13, Folder 9)
    Correspondents include: Robert Gamble; S.P. Gregory; Gene and [George?] Griffin; A.G. Grinnan; Evelyn Hale; Hetty Cary Harrison; Ella Havisham; Jane R. Haxall; Rosalie Haxall; Eva Mary Anna Mason Heth (1836-1915); Mary Heywood (with a photograph of her on her 78th birthday); E.[L.] Holmes; R.R. Howison; J. Johns, Jr.; S. Harvey Johnson; William T. Joyner; W.M. Justis; Bessie D. Kane; J.D.L. Kane; Sallie G. Kean; and Ethel Kilburn. Topics include the Civil War (Robert Gamble, June 19, 1863); reminiscences about the Civil War and General Stuart, and a discussion about genealogy (A.G. Grinnan, 1892-1893); family reading (R.R. Howison, January 30, 1878); discussion of Reuben Lindsay Walker (1827-1890), commander of the Third Corps artillery, and his opposition to the peace commission, known as the [Hampton Roads Conference] during the Civil War and political issues that will arise at the conclusion of the war (William T. Joyner, February 3, 1865); and the poor state of the Confederate army, due in part to desertions (William T. Joyner, February 25, 1865).
  - Miscellaneous correspondents of the Graham family, chiefly letters from various family members and James Duncan Graham (1799-1865), United States Engineer Corps, to his wife, Frances Wickham Graham (1808-1895), 1859-1871; 1 folder(s) (Box 13, Folder 10)
    Correspondents include: Frances Wickham Graham; [Hartley] Graham; James Duncan Graham; Salva Graham; and William F. Wickham. Topics include chiefly family news but also some references to the work of James Duncan Graham as a member of the United States Engineer Corps (April 13, 1862; April 9, 1865; May 9, 1865); the condition of the South at the conclusion of the Civil War (June 2, 1865); and papers concerning the pension of James Duncan Graham (1867-1871).
  - Miscellaneous correspondents of the Hubard family, 1878-1883; 1 folder(s) (Box 13, Folder 11)
    Correspondents include: E.W. Hubard and J.L. Hubard.
  - Miscellaneous Correspondents: L-M, 1854-1984; 1 folder(s) (Box 14, Folder 1)
    Correspondents include: Robert B. Lancaster; Elizabeth W. Lay; R. Bruce Lockhart; A.C. Leigh; William Leigh; Ellen McCaw; Rose M. MacDonald; F. Mark; Captain G. [Marvel]; Dido Mason; E.K.N. Massie; Alice W. Meade; Susan W. Miller; Edgar Miller; F.B. Minor; Mary W. Minor; and M.M. Morris. Topics include work on the book about old homes of Hanover (Robert B. Lancaster, January 8, 1984); the fire at Hickory Hill (Elizabeth W. Lay, February 17, 1875); and notification of an ankle injury of Captain W. Leigh Wickham in Chattanooga, Tennessee while serving as paymaster for the Confederate army (Edgar Miller, May 2, 1863).
  - Miscellaneous correspondents of the Lee family, 1822-1876; 1 folder(s) (Box 14, Folder 2)
    Correspondents include: Agnes Lee, Annie C. Lee, Ann H. Lee, C.C. Lee; Mary Custis Lee; Richard Henry Lee (1794-1865) concerning the state literary fund and his proposed memoir of Richard A. Lee; Robert E. Lee, Jr. concerning the death of William F. Wickham (July 16, 1873); and William H.F. "Rooney" Lee (1837-1891).
  - Miscellaneous correspondents: N-R, 1860-1868; 1 folder(s) (Box 14, Folder 3)
    Correspondents include: Elizabeth B. Nicholas, concerning the fall of New Orleans to Federal forces (April 30, 1862); Helen N. Patterson; Lt. Colonel William H. Payne; Virginia Porcher; Lucy Carter Renshaw (1838-1965) concerning damages suffered by the "Shirley" plantation during the Civil War battles (July 4, 1862); Amelie Louise Rives Troubetzkoy (1863-1945); and M.C. Rives.
  - Miscellaneous correspondents of the Nelson family, 1835-1875; 1 folder(s) (Box 14, Folder 4)
    Correspondents include: Carrie P. Nelson; F. Nelson; F.P. Nelson; Jane E. Nelson; Jenny Nelson concerning the capture of Confederate George Washington "Wash" Nelson near Smithfield (November 6, 1863) and the raids of the Yankee soldiers in the neighborhood against the local residents (undated Civil War letter); M.W. Nelson concerning the death of Lucy Carter Wickham (January 17, 1835); Mary C. Nelson; Robert Nelson on board the ship Oriental with his friend John Lewis [Points?] (August 29, 1851); Rose Nelson; Virginia L. Nelson; and W. Nelson.
  - Miscellaneous Correspondents of the Page family, 1859-1920; 1 folder(s) (Box 14, Folder 5)
    Correspondents include: Anne Rose Page; Elizabeth Burwell Page; John Page; Judith Nelson Page; Leila Page; and Thomas Nelson Page concerning his book about Italy and his visit to England (January 9, 1920).
  - Miscellaneous correspondents: S-V, 1840-1937; 1 folder(s) (Box 14, Folder 6)
    Correspondents include: George William Shelton; Amelie Louise Sigourney; M.M. Smith; Walter N. Sprinkel; A.M. Stearns; Alexander H.H. Stuart writes of his fear of the future, suggests that Williams Carter Wickham and himself travel to Washington on business to meet with some of the Yankee magnates and discuss ways to end the Civil War and expresses his sorrow over the sundering of the Union (January 23, 1865); Alta E. Stumpf concerning the awakening of Russia and its development (June 29, 1931); J.V. Swearingen; Louisa Nivison Tazewell (1804-1873) describing the death of her father, former Virginia governor, Littleton Waller Tazewell (1774-1860) in her letter (May 16, 1860); Fannie W. Toler; and C. Vanderbilt, Jr.
  - Miscellaneous Correspondents: of the Taylor family, 1826-1881; 1 folder(s) (Box 14, Folder 7)
    Correspondents include: Belle Taylor; Bertie Taylor; Edmund P. Taylor; Elizabeth Taylor; Henry Taylor; Henry Taylor, Jr., John Taylor; Julianna Dunlap Leiper Taylor (1801-1883); R.I. Taylor; and Susan W. Taylor. One letter from Henry Taylor, Jr., July 31, 1877, includes a very detailed discussion about Professor Colonel Peters at the University of Virginia.
  - Miscellaneous correspondents: Unidentified, with most letters undated, 1856-1980, undated; 1 folder(s) (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous correspondents: W, 1848-1945; 1 folder(s) (Box 14, Folder 9)
    Correspondents include: Davy Wallace; S. Gardner Waller; Louisa Webb; C.E. Wellford; Mary T. Williams; Captain W.L. Wingfield; Alice B. Winston; Philip B. Winston; and Beulah H.J. Woolston.
  - Miscellaneous Correspondents of the Wickham family and allied families, 1834-1866; 1 folder(s) (Box 14, Folder 10)
    Correspondents include: A.C.L. Wickham; Elizabeth S. Wickham; Fanny Wickham concerning the death of Ella Wickham (March 27, 1851); George Wickham; Julia L. Wickham; J.L. Wickham; L.A.C. Wickham; [L.V.] Wickham; M.F. Wickham; and Sarah Wickham.
  - Personal correspondence of James Lyons (1801-1882) with William F. Wickham, 1873-1878; 1 folder(s) (Box 14, Folder 11)
    Topics include a description of the meeting of the trustees of the Peabody Fund for Education in the South, particularly Bishop Henry Benjamin Whipple of Minnesota and his life among the Indians (August 12, 1876).
  - Personal correspondence of Jonathan Mason (1795-1884) with William F. Wickham, 1875-1878; 1 folder(s) (Box 14, Folder 12)
    Topics include climate change (January 31, 1872); details of the career of his friend Custis, who died in 1872 and was a water commissioner in Boston (February 8, 1872); the influence of John C. Calhoun in ruining the whole South and his own state by men following his "evil counsel" (January 1, 1875); discussions of reading and current politics (January 8, 1875); description of Wickham's losses during the fire in February (March 13, 1875); mentions of Lord Byron, Charles Lamb, William Cullen Bryant and other literary figures (March 22, 1875); description of the Bunker Hill centennial (June 7, 1875); detailed discussion of the career of Patrick Henry (January 1, 1878); religious reading (March 13, 1878); and Richard Henry Dana, Jr. (December 11, 1878).
  - Personal correspondence of William Cabell Rives, 1854-1857, 1867; 1 folder(s) (Box 14, Folder 13)
    The letters are chiefly social or agricultural but one, May 30, 1867, touches upon politics and international events and mentions Rives reading the biography of James Madison.
  - Personal Correspondence of Littleton Waller Tazewell (1774-1860) with William F. Wickham, 1817-1849; 1 folder(s) (Box 14, Folder 14)